A Guide to the Working Papers of Virginia Governor George F. Allen, 1994-1997
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Working Papers of Virginia Governor George F. Allen, 1994-1997
The Library of Virginia
35864
3.675 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1994-1998: Allen)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Georgia Root, Assistant Secretary of the Commonwealth, Richmond, Virginia, 19 June 1998.
Biographical Information
George Felix Allen was born March 8, 1952 in Whittier, California to famed NFL football coach George H. Allen and his wife Henrietta (Lumbroso) Allen. He graduated from the University of Virginia in 1971 and the University of Virginia School of Law in 1977. Allen served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1982-1991 and served a short term in the U.S. House of Delegates in the early 1990s. In November 1993, Allen beat Attorney General Mary Sue Terry to become Governor. Governor Allen served until January 1998 and was succeeded by Governor James S. Gilmore. Governor Allen has been married to Susan (Brown) Allen since 1986 and they have three children, Forrest, Tyler, and Brooke. The family resides in Mount Vernon, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence, memoranda, proposals, reports, and other documents created and maintained by Governor George Allen as his "working papers." The working papers relate to specific activities, issues, and policies that were of particular interest to Governor Allen and members of his administration. Often the topics covered in the working papers were hot-button issues or policies that received a significant amount of press and attention. Almost half of the files pertain to the Opportunity Virginia economic initiative, while the other files contain information on a variety of issues arranged by appropriate secretariat.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Opportunity Virginia Working Papers
Series II. Secretariat and Agency Working Papers
Contents List
- Series I. Opportunity Virginia Files, 1994-1996., Extent: 1.75 cu. ft. (Box 1-5)
  Contains reports, plans, correspondence and other material associated with Governor Allen's 1994 economic development initiative, Opportunity Virginia. The initiative was divided into two sections, the first being the creation of regional economic development advisory councils (REDACs). The regional councils were composed of business leaders, economic development professionals, elected officials, educators, and citizens. The councils were expected to provide support and guidance for regional economic development projects. The second part of the Opportunity Virginia initiative was the creation of a strategic plan structured around ten core economic sectors including agribusiness, aerospace, biotechnology, tourism, manufacturing, and information technology. Working groups from each of the sectors participated in the development of a long-range plan titled "Opportunity Virginia: A Strategic Plan for Jobs and Prosperity," which was revealed by Governor Allen in December 1994.
  Arranged according to subject and then alphabetically or numerically within.
  - Regional Economic Development Advisory Council (REDAC) Files.
    - General File. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - REDAC 1. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - REDAC 2. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - REDAC 3. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - REDAC 4. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - REDAC 5. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - REDAC 6. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - REDAC 7. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - REDAC 8. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - REDAC 9. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - REDAC 10. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - REDAC 11. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - REDAC 12. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - REDAC 13. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - REDAC 14. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - REDAC 15. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - REDAC 16. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - REDAC 17. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - REDAC 18. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sector Files.
    - Agribusiness Sector. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Aerospace Sector. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Biotechnology Sector. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Industry Sector. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Information Technology and Telecommunications Sector. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - International Trade Sector. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Manufacturing Sector. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Maritime Sector. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Tourism Sector. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Opportunity Virginia Files.
    - Agribusiness Lunch. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Blue Ridge Commission Meeting. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Disney's America. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Disney's America. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Disney's America. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Governor's Business Lunches. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Information Technology Infrastructure Initiative. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Information Technology and Telecommunications Lunch. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Information Technology and Telecommunications Summits. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - McGraw Hill Strategic Plan. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Opportunity Virginia: A Strategic Plan for Jobs and Prosperity (Full Text). (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Opportunity Virginia Roll-out. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Previous Virginia Strategic Plans. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Regional Partnerships Quarterly Seminar Meetings. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Road Map to the Future: A Strategic Plan for Virginia's Information Technology Infrastructure." (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Rural Economic Development Fund. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Science and Technology Task Force. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Shenandoah Valley Partnership. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Technology Summits. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Telecommunications Meeting Letters. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Chamber of Commerce Strategic Plan. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Virginia Community College System/Virginia Works. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Virginia Economic Development Competitiveness Study. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series II. Secretariat Files, 1994-1997., Extent: 1.925 cu. ft. (Box 5-11)
  Contains a variety of subject files associated with particular secretariats and/or agencies. Files contain correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other material pertaining to issues of interest to the Governor's Office. Topics of note include business and industry in Virginia, the Goals 2000 education initiative, a Department of Justice investigation at Central State Hospital, and interstate agreements on detainers.
  Arranged according to cabinet secretariat or topic and then alphabetically within.
  - Commerce and Trade/Economic Development Files.
    - African Offices. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Alexandria Convention Center. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - American Type Culture Collection. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - American Type Culture Collection (Discussions). (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Canadian Football League (Hampton Roads). (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Columbia Gas (Gemstone). (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - CSX/Conrail Merger. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - CSX/Conrail Merger (Clippings). (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - CSX/Conrail Merger (Memoranda). (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - CSX/Conrail Merger (Memoranda, Skunda to Allen). (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Diplomatic Issues (Diplomatic Receptions). (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Diplomatic Issues: Visit of the Consul General of Japan and Minister, Head of Chancery. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Dominion Semiconductor. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Dominion Semiconductor. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dominion Semiconductor. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Dominion Semiconductor (Clippings). (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Dominion Semiconductor (Memorandum of Understanding). (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - DuPont/Virginia Power. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Economic Development (Miscellaneous Memoranda). (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Family Dollar Stores. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Federal Express. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Frito-Lay. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Fujitsu. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - IBM/Toshiba. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Jack Kent Cooke Stadium. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - James River Corporation. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Matrix Capital. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - NAFTA Reunion/Diplomatic Reception. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - North Carolina Business Incentives. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Opportunity Fund. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Orkland Corporation. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Orkland Corporation. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - ROCCO (Shenandoah Rail Company). (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Science Applications International Corporation. (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Semiconductor Endowment. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Shreveport Pirates. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Solarex (AMOCO). (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Star Shipping. (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Virginia Economic Development Partnership. (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Washington Global Center. (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - WESTVACO. (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - White Oak Semiconductors (Announcement). (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Whitehall-Robbins. (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Education Policy Files.
    - Board of Education Assessments, 1995-1996. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bosher's Board Battle. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Champion Schools: Decision Memoranda. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Champion Schools: Interim Report Draft. 1994. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Family Foundation, 1997. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Goals 2000. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Goals 2000. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Goals 2000. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Goals 2000: Dr. Bosher's Presentation. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Goals 2000: Revision. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Goals 2000: State Documents. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Guidance Counselors. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - General Education Issues. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - General Education Issues. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - General Education Issues: Standards of Accreditation. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - General Education Policy. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - General Education Policy. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Opinion on Champion Schools, 1995. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Higher Education Funding Proposals, 1997. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (IDEA). (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Jobs for Grads, 1996. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Office for Civil Rights Investigation. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - SAT Report, 1994. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - School-to-Work Program. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - School-to-Work Program. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - School-to-Work Program. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - School-to-Work Program: Talking Points, 1996. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Teletechnet, 1994. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Teletechnet: Old Dominion University, 1994. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Health and Human Resources Files.
    - Aging, Dept. for the. (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Biosolids Use Regulations: Hanover County, 1996. (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Central State Hospital: Dept. of Justice Investigation. (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Central State Hospital: Dept. of Justice Investigation. (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Central State Hospital: Dept. of Justice Investigation. (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Central State Hospital: Dept. of Justice Investigation. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Central State Hospital: Dept. of Justice Investigation. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Drees, Ida Sue, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Jaffe, Dr. Russell, 1994. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Dept. of. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Dept. of,: SAFECARE. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Midgett Case, Update on, 1994. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Sewage Handling and Disposal Regulations, Possible Violations of by Norfolk Southern Railway. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Status of U.S. Dept. of Justice Lawsuits. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Veterans Care Center, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Finance Files.
    - Air and Space Annex Project, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Smithsonian Air and Space Museum Annex: Memorandum of Understanding Draft Review, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Natural Resources Files.
    - AVTEX Suit, 1997. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Clean Air Act, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of,: Report on Conservation Reserve Program. (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Environmental Liabilities at Fort Pickett. (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - EPA: Any Credible Evidence (ACE) Rule. (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - King William Reservoir, 1997. (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Public Access Coves and Inlets along the James River. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Public Safety Files.
    - Attorney General: Interstate Agreements on Detainers, 1995. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Attorney General: Interstate Agreements on Detainers, 1996. (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Attorney General: Interstate Agreements on Detainers, 1997. (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Corrections, Dept. of,: Offender Management System, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - National Guard Troop Activity (Armory Closures). (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Public Safety Issues. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Settlement with ACLU over Mecklenburg Strip Search, 1995. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - State Police, Dept. of,: Report on Security Procedures at State Forensic Facilities, 1994. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Transportation Files.
    - COSCO, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Enhancement Grants and Transportation Safety Grants, 1994. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Maersk-Sealand, 1996. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Metropolitan Washington Regional Transportation Authority, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Nextea Proposal: Clinton Administration, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - North Carolina Officials, Meeting with, 1994. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - NOVA Metro Area Regional Authority, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Privitization Proposal for I-895 Connector, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - PPTA Proposals, 1995. (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Route 802 in Washington County, 1997. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Telecommunications Act of 1996 and ITS, 1996. (Box 11, Folder 16)